Ravindra Singh Rawat



Contact

Address:

NH-72 Chakrata Road Jhajra, Premnagar Dehradun, Uttarakhand 248007

Phone:

<u>9820793187/9654103288</u>

Email:

<u>ravindrarawat48@gmail.com</u>

Website:

https://sites.google.com/view/ravindr a-singh-rawat

LinkedIn:

https://www.linkedin.com/in/ravindra-singh-rawat-3803b73a/

YouTube Channel:

https://www.youtube.com/c/ravirawa t19

Githut:

https://github.com/rsr1987

Orcid Id:

0000-0003-4154-7216

Languages

Hindi, English, Spanish Basic Level

Hobbies

Exploring New Technology, Discussion & Debate, Singing.

Brief Profile

Ravindra Singh Rawat is enriched with a total of around 10 years of work experience. Out of which, He has had a corporate experience of three-and-a-half years and more than six years of academics respectively. His professional journey steamed off with 'Indiabulls Securities Ltd., Gurgaon DLF Cyber City, as a Relationship Manager. Thereupon, He joined 'Asian Business Exhibitions & Conferences Pvt. Ltd.', as an Event Manager.

He began his academic career as an Assistant Professor at Uttaranchal University, Dehradun. Presently, he has been working with the prestigious 'University of Petroleum and Energy Studies' as a Visiting faculty with their 'School for Life'. He is also a Course Instructor for Amity Online MBA Program. He acquired his master's in Business administration from a wellrecognized B-school, 'New Delhi Institute of Management with a specialization in 'Marketing Management and International Business. He has also been pursuing his Ph.D. from Uttarakhand Technical University, Dehradun. His area of research being 'Resurgence of MSME with Digital Technologies in Uttarakhand. He has earned various specialization certificate courses online from the world's topmost educators. To name a few... 'Entrepreneurship in Emerging Economies' from Harvard Business School, 'Digital Marketing' from the University of Illinois, 'Search Engine Optimisation from the University of California, 'Business Statistics and Analysis' from Rice University, 'Data Science & AI foundations for Business' from reputed IBM.

He has been continually contributing to research and to his credit has published a chapter in the book titled 'People Management in 21st Century - Practice & Challenges' (Tata McGrow) on Entrepreneurship. He has also presented/published research papers in National & International conferences/seminars/journals. He is also a reviewer of the Web of Science journal Gurukul Business Review.

Career Objective

Looking for a full-time position in Academics and Research where I can utilize my experience in corporate and academic sectors for the ultimate benefit of my prospective students and organization apart from my personal satisfaction and growth.

Skill Highlights

- Marketing Management
- Legal Aspects of Business
- Digital Marketing
- Search Engine Optimization
- Artificial Intelligence in Business
- Data Science.
- Advance Excel.
- SPSS,SPSS AMOS, SMART PLS

Education

- **Ph.D. (Pursuing)** enrolled in 2016, Course Work- Research Methodology exam with 78 % from **Uttarakhand Technical University** in Management.
- PGDM/MBA in 2012 from New Delhi Institute of Management (Accredited by NBA, GOI & Approved by AICTE & AIU) with First Division.
- BBA in 2010 from H. N. B. Gharwal University with First Division.
- HSC (Science) in 2004 from S.V.M Inter College Vikasnagar, Dehradun (Uttaranchal Board) with **Second Division.**
- SSC (Science) in 2002 S.G.R.R. Inter College Shaspur, Dehradun (Uttaranchal Board) with **First Division**.

PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATION & SPECIALIZATION PROGRAMS

- 1) Entrepreneurship in Emerging Economies, Harvard University, Harvard School of Business, US.
- 2) Specialization Program in Digital Marketing with 7 Courses, University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign: Marketing in a Digital World, Digital Analytics for Marketing Professionals: Marketing Analytics in Theory, Digital Analytics for Marketing Professionals: Marketing Analytics in Practice Digital Media and Marketing Principle Digital Media and Marketing Strategies, Marketing in an Analog World, Digital Marketing Capstone.
- 3) Specialization Program in Search Engine Optimization (SEO) with 5 Courses, University of California, Davis: Introduction to Search Engine Optimization., Search Engine Optimization Fundamentals. Optimizing a Website for Search., Advanced Content and Social Tactics to Optimize SEO, Website Optimization Client Report Project.
- 4) Project Work Coursera on "Build a Full Website using WordPress".
- 5) Project Work Coursera on "Getting Started in Google Analytics".
- 6) Brand Management: Aligning Business, Brand & Behaviors, University of London, London Business School.
- 7) Specialization Program in Key Technologies for Business Specialization with 3 Courses, IBM: Introduction to Cloud Computing, Introduction to Artificial Intelligence (AI), What is Data Science.
- **8)** Specialization Program in Data Science Specialization with 4 Courses, IBM: What is Data Science, Tools for Data Science, Data Science Introduction to Methodology, Databases and SQL for Data Science
- 9) Specialization Program in IBM AI Foundations for Business Specialization with 3 Courses: Introduction to Artificial Intelligence (AI), What is Data Science, The AI Ladder: A Framework for Deploying AI in your Enterprise
- **10) Specialization Program in Business Statistics and Analysis with 5 Courses, Rice University.** Introduction to Data Analysis Using Excel., Basic Data Descriptors, Statistical Distributions, and Application to Business Decisions., Business Applications of Hypothesis Testing and Confidence Interval Estimation, Linear Regression for Business Statistics., Business Statistics and Analysis Capstone.
- **11)** Specialization Program in **Virtual Teacher** with **5 Courses University of California, Irvine**. Foundations of Virtual Instruction, Emerging Trends & Technologies in the Virtual K-12 Classroom, Advanced Instructional Strategies in the Virtual Classroom, Performance Assessment in the Virtual Classroom, Virtual Teacher Final Project.
- **12)** Communication Strategies for a Virtual Age, **University of Toronto.**
- 13) Introduction to Public Speaking, University of Washington.
- **14)** Self-Awareness and the Effective Leader, **Rice University.**
- 15) Learning How to Learn: Powerful mental tools to help you master tough subjects, McMaster University & University of California San Diego.

RESEARCH PAPERS / CONFERENCES

- 1) Presented Research Paper at NIT Hamirpur RTMSS-2021 National Conference Recent Trends in Management & Social Sciences titled, "Digital Marketing for the inclusive growth of Micro Small Medium Enterprises."
- 2) Presented Research Paper in IUU NASMEI International E-Conference on THE AGE OF DIGITAL TRANSFORMATION Impact of Emerging Technologies in Marketing title "Role of Digital Technologies in the resurgence of Small Businesses"
- 3) A Research Paper on "Role of Social Media in Advertising" is published in JETIR, April 2019 Volume 6, Issue 4 (ISSN -2349-5162) UGC Approved.
- **4)** A Research Paper on "Comparative Study Online Advertising and Conventional Advertising Strategies" in JETIR May 2019 Volume 6, Issue 5 (ISSN -2349-55162) UGC Approved.
- 5) A chapter is written in Book Titled "PEOPLE MANAGEMENT IN 21st CENTURY- PRACTICE AND CHALLENGES" published under TATA MCRAW on ENTREPRENEURSHIP, ISBN 13:978-93-5316-121-7 ISBN-10: 93-5316-121-5.
- 6) Presented research paper on Entrepreneurship, Environment and Sustainable Development: Can it go hand in hand? at one-day International Conference on "People Management and Sustainable Economy: Issues and Challenges for Organizations in 21st Century" held in New Delhi Institute of Management on 18 March 2017.

FDP/SEMINAR/ CONFERENCE

- 1) Attended 2-Days Workshop on "Structural Equation Modeling with AMOS & SmartPLS" from 8th to 9th May 2021. organized by Commacad
- 2) Attended 2-Days Workshop on "SPSS Master" organized by Commacad from 26th to 28th, Mar 2021.
- 3) Attended Webinar on 3rd Felicitation Ceremony on Teacher's Day organized by Divya Himgiri in collaboration with Commission for Scientific and Technical Terminology, MHRD Government of India, Uttarakhand Department of School Education, Uttarakhand Statutory Education Council, Uttarakhand Technical University, Sridev Suman University, Society for Research and Development in Science Dehradun, Uttarakhand, 5 Sep 2020.
- 4) Attended Webinar Series on "Advanced Technology as a part of Startup in India" organized by Indrashil University (IU) Gujarat, 18-29 August 2020.
- 5) Attended 2-Days National webinar organized under the aegis of Commission for Scientific and Technical Terminology, Ministry of Education Government of India (New Delhi) and Women Institute of Technology Dehradun, Uttarakhand, 17 18 August 2020.
- 6) Attended National Faculty Development Program on "Case Writing & Case Teaching" organized by Globsyn Business School, Kolkata West Bengal during 7-8 Aug 2020.
- 7) Acted as Key Note Speaker for MDP organized by Eran Health on "Digital Techniques to Accelerate Business Post Pandemic, 20 Jun 2020.
- 8) Attended one-day National Level Symposium on "Design Thinking in Digital Marketing" organized by Vignan's Foundation Science Technology & Research (Deemed to be University) on 24 May 2020.
- 9) Honored with Certificate of Appreciation for organizing "International Conference on Information Technology and Management for the Sustainable Development ICITMSD-2019)" Jointly organized by Life Way Tech India Uttaranchal University, Uttaranchal Institute of Management, Dehradun during 9-10 Aug 2019.
- **10)** Attended **10-Days** Faculty Development Program on "Data Analysis Techniques Using SPSS" organized by Uttaranchal Institute of Management, Uttaranchal University, Dehradun during **22-31 July 2019.**
- **11)** Certificate Program from **IIT Bombay**, on **LaTeX**, Organized by IIT Bombay funded by National Mission on Education through ICT, MHRD, Govt Of India. on **15/Jan/2019**.
- 12) Attended Teachers' Congruence & Faculty Development Program organized by Uttaranchal University in association with The Institute of Company Secretaries of India, Dehradun Chapter under the aegis of LAW COLLEGE DEHRADUN during 16th July 2018.
- 13) Attended 7-Days FACULTY DEVELOPMENT PROGRAMME on "Innovative Techniques and Magnitude of Teaching Methodology in Higher Education" organized by Uttaranchal University from 16th -22nd July 2018.
- **14)** Attended course work on Research Methodology organized at **Uttarakhand Technical University**, Dehradun during **26th -30th Dec 2017**.
- 15) Attended One-Day National Seminar on "GST" held in Uttaranchal University on 28thNov 2017.
- **16)** Attended **5-Days** Faculty Development Program on "Research Methodology & Data Analysis using SPSS" held in Uttaranchal University on **27th July 2017**.
- **17)** Attended **6-Days** Faculty Development Program on "Research Methodology" held in Uttaranchal University on 04th -9th Dec 2017.

ACADEMIC WORK EXPERIENCE

University of Petroleum & Energy Sciences Visiting Faculty Jan-2020-Till Date (SFL, SoB, SoE, SoCS) (1 Year & 6 Months)

Role & Responsibilities:

- 1) Designed and delivered a course with overwhelming students' feedback on "Working with Data" using MS Excel.
- **2)** Developing course and content for the programs teaching in Blended mode on **(LMS Blackboard**) and offline Face to Face mode.
- 3) Preparing Course Plan, Lecture Plan as per the credit allotted to the course, updating students on regular basis, conducted various assessment activities, and designed online/ offline assessment and evaluation scheme.
- 4) Preparing and Maintaining the records of assessment and evaluation plans as per the guidelines of IQAC compliance.
- 5) Regular monitoring and mapping of Course Outcomes, Program Outcomes, and Program Specific Outcomes for the better delivery and performance of the students.
- **6)** Community Building (Interaction and Communication) with the students and making them understand about Technology Tools (Synchronous and Asynchronous) for better delivery.
- 7) Making announcements about various differentiated Instruction (At Risk, High Performing, and Special Needs Students to make them aware of their courses and take immediate actions as per their requirement.

Uttaranchal UniversityAssistant ProfessorJuly-2015-Jan-2020(Faculty of Management & Business Studies)(4 Years & 6 Months)

Role & Responsibilities:

- 1) As Head Cultural Academic Affairs, Conceptualized, Designed various activities and events for the ultimate benefit of the students like International Conference, Academic and Nonacademic Club's activities, Entrepreneurial Events, Social Engagement, etc.
- 2) Delivered lectures on subjects like Marketing Management, Consumer Behavior, Fundamentals of Retailing, Marketing Communication and Advertising, Business Communication, Business Laws, and Corporate Laws.
- 3) Have Set University Examination Question Papers for BBA, B. Com (H), LLB and MBA courses in Marketing Management, Marketing Communication and Advertising, Fundamental of Retailing, Consumer Behavior, Digital Marketing, Business Laws and Corporate Laws.
- 4) Criteria Coordinator for IQAC Criteria -7, "Institutional Values and Best Practices".
- 5) Supervise and guide the students for their summer training projects and dissertation reports.
- **6)** Worked as Associate Editor for University Website.

CORPORATE WORK EXPERIENCE

Asian Business Exhibition & Conference Ltd. Assistant Event Manager (Sep 2013- Jun 2015)
(Times Property Exhibition) (Corporate Sales)
(1 Year & 10 Months)

Roles and Responsibilities

- 1) Worked as an Assistant Event Manager for Asian Business Exhibition & Conference Ltd. Gurgaon Office. I was responsibly strategizing the growth in sales, marketing policies and analyzing prospective clients for the exhibitions.
- 2) To liaison with various corporate houses and sending them invitations for participating in exhibitions and conferences.
- 3) To present floor plan and negotiate with the Advertising & Promotional Heads of the company for the exhibitions.
- 4) To finalize the space allocation, documentation, and payment procedure with the exhibitors.
- 5) To create new Paper, Pamphlet, Hoarding Advertisements for the promotion of exhibitions and exhibitors,
- 6) To plan for the Branding & Promotion of exhibitions & exhibitors in Times Property News Paper.
- 7) To execute appropriate planning, organizing, supervising, directing, and controlling activities in the exhibitions.
- 8) To make a regular follow-up with prospective clients to increase client base as well as to generate higher revenue for the organization

Relationship Manage

(Jan2012-Sep2013)

(1 Year & 9 Months)

Roles & Responsibilities:

- 1) Worked as a Relationship Manager in **Indiabulls Securities Ltd**. Gurgaon Sales Head Office. My responsibilities included inter alia ensuring effective analysis of prospects for equity and real estate market to deliver good performance.
- 2) Acquiring new HNI clients and formulating strategies to increase the client base for equity and real estate markets.
- 3) Dealing with the existing and prospective clients and update them for the best lucrative investment projects in equity and real estate markets.
- 4) Reviewing regular client portfolios and providing advisory services to them in equity and real estate markets.
- 5) Approaching clients on a need-based product through strategic financial planning.
- 6) Assessing the portfolio risk, according to the changing market scenario

ACHIEVEMENTS/CO-CURRICULAR /EXTRA-CURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

- 1) Received letter of appreciation for organizing *National Academic Fest "FESTLA -2K19 as Head Cultural Academic Affairs in Uttaranchal University* organized by Uttaranchal Institute of Management 16th Nov 2019.
- 2) Received letter of appreciation for organizing International Conference on 'Information Technology and management for the sustainable development (ICITMSD)' organized by Uttaranchal Institute of Management concluded on 10th Aug 2019.
- **3)** Earned **10 IBM Badges** on Data Science, Artificial Intelligence, Could Computing for Businesses.
- 4) Won AIMA National Management Game 2011 award at Zonal level.
- 5) 1st Rank in Bachelor of Business Administration college level.
- 6) 1st Rank in HSC (Science) School level.
- 7) Participated in 'NDTV TALK-SHOW Money Mantra" on Financial Inclusion.
- 8) Awarded "Best Performer" for archiving, CEO sales target in Indiabulls Securities Ltd.
- 9) Basic Course of Spanish from "ALHAMBRA Institudo de la Cultura y la lengua española".
- **10) Internship:** Evaluating and Analyzing, Segmentation Model Of **COCA COLA RED** (Right Execution Daily) from **Hindustan Coca Cola Beverages Pvt. Ltd. Noida Sec-63**, in **2011**.

TECHNOLOGICAL COMPATABILTY

1)	ERP Campsys.	5)	SEM with AMOS.	9) WordPress.
2)	LSM Blackboard.	6)	SEM with SmartSPL.	10) SEO Analytics.
3)	MS Office & Advance Excel.	7)	Google Analytics.	
4)	SPSS for Data Analysis.	8)	Google Sties.	

PERSONAL INFORMATION

Permanent Address: Village – Jhajra, P. O. - Suddhowala, Dehradun, Uttarakhand 248007.

Father's Name & Occupation: Shri. R. S. Rawat & Bank Accountant. (Retired)

Mother's Name & Occupation: Smt. Beena Rawat, Social Worker, Uttarakhand Freedom fighter, LIC Advisor.

Nationality: Indian. Marital Status: Unmarried.

DECLARATION

I hereby declare that the above-mentioned information is correct, up to best of my knowledge and belief. I bear the responsibility for the correctness of the above-mentioned particulars.

Place: Dehradun	Ravindra Singh Rawat

Date:__/___.